Based in: London, NW10 7GL, UK

Marius OLARIU

marius.lucian.olariu @gmail.com linkedin.com/in/mlo1994

Summary

I am a Software Engineer with 5+ years of experience in developing Web and Desktop apps. One of my best professional strengths is the passion for learning and my ideal place is one where growth is encouraged and supported. My main technology skills are Java, Groovy, Spring, AWS, JavaScript and SQL but at the same time I love exploring and learning new technologies. I have EU pre-settled status which gives me the right to work and live in UK without a visa.

Employment

Backend Software Engineer

Vodafone

Feb 2023 - present

Backend software development for the micro-services responsible for the checkout page on vodafone.co.uk. In this role I work as part of a Scrum Agile team which releases weekly. This role has allowed me to get involved in the release process and the subsequent monitoring necessary via tools like Datadog.

Technologies used: Java, Spring, AWS, SQL, Git, Datadog

Product developed: https://www.vodafone.co.uk

Senior Java Software Engineer

Zuhlke Engineering Ltd

Oct 2022 - Dec 2022

Short employment for Software Consulting company due to lack of demand for contract Software Engineers given the economic situation at the time.

Full Stack Software Engineer

IOVIA

Feb 2022 - Oct 2022

Full-stack development for a Phase I eSource and clinical trial automation system which is used by the biggest pharmaceutical companies in the world (e.g. 3 of top 5 pharmaceutical companies). I collaborated efficiently with Project Managers, Biomedical Engineers and Product Owner in order to deliver the best results for clients.

Technologies used: Groovy, Grails, Java, AWS, JavaScript, SQL, Git, HTML, CSS

Product developed: https://www.clinspark.com/

Software Engineer

Diffblue

Aug 2020 - Feb 2022

In this role, I developed software in Java in an Agile environment for Diffblue Cover, a tool powered by AI that automatically generates (unit) tests for Java code. I made a consistent commitment to growth by embracing continuous learning (i.e. each Sprint I studied a new topic relevant for my work) and by taking new responsibilities (e.g. lead stand-ups and Sprint Retrospectives). Last, but not least, I set up and maintained an online environment where the product could be demoed.

Technologies used: Java, Spring (basic usage), JUnit, Maven, Git

Product developed: https://www.diffblue.com/products/

Junior Full Stack Engineer

New Verve Consulting

Aug 2019 - Aug 2020

Played an important role in the development and launch of a cloud add-on for Jira. The add-on allows you to bring context to Jira tickets by linking them to customer data. I helped through pair-programming sessions one of my colleagues to transition from a Technical Consultant position to a Developer one. Managed my time successfully between writing my MSc dissertation and this position.

Technologies used: JavaScript, React, Node, Jest, Git, HTML, CSS

Product developed: https://bit.ly/3zKtngM

Junior Software Engineer

SSI Schaefer Romania

Sept. 2017 - Aug 2018

Got exposed to the world of professional software development with Java as well as finished my last year of BSc studies in Computer Science. I worked on the development of software for a vertical lift module (LOGIMAT) that allowed goods in a warehouse to be stored and managed efficiently. Managed my time successfully between this position and my last year of BSc studies.

Technologies used: Java, SQL, JUnit, HQL, Git

Product developed: https://logimat.ssi-schaefer.com/logimat-en-gb

Education

Paisley, Scotland West University Scotland

Sept 2018 - Feb 2020

- Received an MSc degree with distinction in "Mobile Web Development"
- MSc thesis: Development and Evaluation of the User Experience of a Mobile Booking Application
- Courses: Web Development, Mobile Networks and Smartphone Apps, Human-Computer Interaction etc.

Timisoara, Romania

Polytechnic University

Sept 2014 - June 2018

- Received a Bachelor degree with distinction in "Computer and Software Engineering"
- BSc project: HelpMeSee Navigation assistant for visually impaired people
- Courses: Computer Programming, Algorithms, Operating Systems, Databases etc.

Nijmegen, The Netherlands

Radboud University

Feb 2017 - Jul 2017

• exchange semester through Erasmus programme

Linköping, Sweden

Linköping University

Sept 2016 - Jan 2017

• exchange semester through Erasmus programme

Technical Experience

Personal Projects

- Plus One Mentor App (2019) Mobile and Web solution for the youth work of YMCA Paisley and also used for my MSc research. This mobile solution allows YMCA volunteers to schedule appointments with mentees and also to provide feedback on them. The Web solution allows the manager to see an activity overview for each YMCA volunteer within his organization. Java API Android, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Firebase Solutions, Git
- **HelpMeSee** (2018) Navigation assistant for visually impaired people, namely an Android application through which the visually impaired user can set a certain destination and will receive real-time voice instruction on how to get to it. Demo video, code and documentation can be found on my GitHub account. Java API Android, MVC architecture, LaTeX documentation, *git*

Additional Experience and Awards

- SFC Scholarship (2018). A scholarship awarded by the Scottish Funding Council (SFC) that covered the tuition fee for my master degree programme.
- Third Prize, inGENIOUSly (2016). My team received this prize at the "inGENIOUSly" competition organized by Continental Automotive Romania.

Volunteering

Paisley, Scotland

YMCA Paisley

Sept 2018 - Aug 2019

- I went to a coding club for young people (7 18 years old) where I helped them learn programming through gamification.
- More info can be found at http://www.paisleyymca.org/

Online

- GitHub: https://github.com/mariusolariu
- Linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/mlo1994

Soft Skills

- languages: Romanian (native), English (fluent)
- driving licence (2012)